啊。
早晨。
嗯。
多謝各位委員啊！
我哋啲路上。
噉啊！
小組咁小組咧係會為戲曲中心嘅管理同埋營運嘅事宜咧係提供意見嘅。
噉啊！而家請誒同事咧，就邀請政府當局同埋西九管理局嘅代表進入會議室嘅。
咁而家咧就請政府當局同埋西九管理局嘅代表咧，係可以咧，係。
噉啊啊，餘國烈先生啦，噉係表演藝術行政嘅總監，咁同埋啊一眾嘅同事嘅。
噉啊！呢一個item咧，我哋都歡迎翻，即係民政事務局常秘馮晴淑儀女士啦。噉啊，柏志高先生啦，西九嘅行政總裁。
噉啊，早晨啦！噉啊，我哋今日會議咧就開到會啦，順利都。咁第一個議程咧就係西九文化區嘅文化軟件發展。
介紹即係呢一份嘅文件嘅，噉我知道你哋都準備咗啲即係電腦嘅投影片嘅，係嘛？咁可以交翻個時間畀你哋介紹啦。
多謝主席。誒嗱誒，上一次我哋嘅聯合小組委員會咧，我哋向各位介紹咗西九嘅硬件嘅發展啦。咁嗱，大家都知道咧，要達到西九文化區嘅一個嘅發為發展為世界級文化藝術區嘅願景咧，一定要喺藝文化嘅軟件嗰方面咧，都要落足功夫嘅。咁今日咧，我哋主要就係嚟介紹咧，係。
喺西九誒文化區管理局咧，喺唔同範疇表演藝術咧，誒佢哋同埋喺呢個視覺藝術方面咧，嗰個文化軟件嘅發展。咁喺過去呢幾年咧，其實西九咧都係誒製作咗好多節目啦，同埋展覽啦，亦都參與咗好多文化交流合作、專業發展，亦都舉辦咗各式各樣嘅社區嘅參與活動嚟到拓。
展西九嘅觀眾羣同埋培育咧文化藝術人才嘅誒，今日特別想提一提咧，就喺表演藝術方面咧，大家知道戲曲中心咧，出年年底咧就會落成㗎啦。咁管理局咧已經喺佢哋嘅表演藝術委員會咧，從performing arts committee下邊咧成立咗一個由業界同埋專業人士組成嘅戲曲中心顧問。
嗯。
Yeah.
programs here.
introduce the paper.
我會 start， actually。
所以我會 start with M plus， just to begin kick off our.
出席我哋聯合小組委員會嘅會議，同大家係去介紹西九嘅文化軟件嘅發展。
Venue operations dealing with the the performing arts venues. So, Louis, ask you to.
希望咧，誒一方面咧，希望咧達到誒西九嘅藝術使命啦，同埋特點啦，亦都希望能夠儘量咧兼顧財政上面嘅可持續性呢啲因素。
Thank you, Chairman. Today we have prepared two presentations. I would like to invite Miss Alison Friedman, our artistic director, to talk about the software and the programme we have done. Thank you. Okay.
此外咧，管理局亦都係增設咗表演藝術總監一個職銜，就咁咧就係確保西九嘅表演藝術節目咧能夠展現活力同埋具前瞻前瞻性，亦都咧能夠希望能夠達到西九嘅藝術願景同埋方針。獲委任為表演藝術總監嘅方美昂女士咧，Alison Friedman咧，今日咧亦都係首次出。
今日喺誒向委員會呈呈交嘅文件嘅第五十四段至五十七段咧，特別係介紹咗西九管理局嘅表演藝術場地租用政策啊！大家都好關心呢個政策咧，因為呢個係會引用於誒喺西九嘅唔同表演場地嘅誒嗰個嘅一套嘅誒政策同埋係安排嚟嘅。咁咧亦都係能同時。
起居中心咧，預計喺誒明年咧係會接受初步嘅場地預訂嘅。噉我首先咧請誒管理局行政總裁柏志高先生咧介紹有幾位嘅同事，今日係會作為大家去做呢個投影片嘅簡介嘅。好，thank you, Mr. I'm just going to introduce my colleagues, and they will take you through the presentation. First of all, of course, Louis here.
You know, Louis, I'm sure, is executive director in the performing arts side. Secondly, is Siranya Raphael, who's the executive director for the M+ Museum. Third, Ms Alison Freeman, who's our new artistic director on the performing arts side. And finally, Ms Lisa Chung, who's the head of
learning programmes.
conversations on South and South East Asia.
based out of Hong Kong and then into Asia.
undertake screenings and conversations here in Hong Kong.
those screenings also reflect an important part of our own.
external advisers, one from Hong Kong University, Dr. Um and Dr. Chow from Baptist Uni.
collection interests and so we we look at programming.
again， I think playing a very significant part about in in relation to the art histories of our place and times.
Canton Express, the next exhibition, a major gift that we brought to the people of Hong Kong, first shown at the Venice Biennale in 2003.
We work with the Hong Kong Arts Development Council, of course, to present the Venice Biennale, very important part of Hong Kong's international presence in the most important international visual arts arena.
Audience building, of course, continues in the pavilion, and for be launched this year with the first Hong Kong popular culture exhibition. Working very closely with colleagues from the Hong Kong Heritage Museums and two.
The weight of lightness currently on at the pavilion, a very important show highlighting our collections of ink art and ink from the perspective of M+. Looking at the visual cultures of ink across 60 years.
We launched also this time R M Plus Matters keynotes with a group of very important architects and the Benesse Foundation that supports the Nao Shima Art Site at Hong Kong University to a packed audience of three hundred people.
So, beginning with capacity building, and I just wanted to start with our various partnerships and collaborations. Beginning with the Design Trust, this year we had Hugh Davis and the team from the Van Dijk and Sampson Wong groups working with us. These are new research looking at design.
建築在香港和珠江三角洲，非常有用。然後當然有實習計劃，非常重要的構建香港的實力。我們在二零一二年開始這個計劃，今年我們有九個實習生在春和夏。
And we had two technical and ten visual arts interns as part of this programme. Docents, we now launched this in two thousand and thirteen, and we now have over one hundred docents. Very proud to be able to work with this kind of audience.
As I mentioned earlier, Samson Young Hong Kong's Venice Biennale presentation very, very successful this time, with over one hundred and thirty-four thousand people visiting. And of course, part of that collaboration with the Hong Kong Arts Development Council also means that we.
screenings at Yamate at the Broadway Cinematheque. We also have our M Plus Matters launched in 2012. Our pedagogical platform, very important research, new scholarship, working with Hong Kong scholars and international colleagues. And this time, we are presented most recently reorient.
OK。
thank you.
哦。
future professionals, our future collectors, our future museum visitors.
We also, I just go back one. I meant to talk about the I.M.P.
collaborations before the venues open of ensuring that West Kowloon is together with Hong Kong for Hong Kong with an international focus.
forum as well that we launched this year with the Harvard Business School Graduate Business School and Hong Kong U. 100 years of I.M.Pe. Very very significant architect. No retrospective done in the world yet, which we will look to doing.
And we have also now developed a talk series that are fundamentally aimed at our docent training, but much broader to anybody in the arts industry who are interested in thinking about audience and learning and museum learning in the twenty-first century.
and then of course the M+ rover continues launched in 2016 and we take our rover to as many schools, primary and secondary and community centres as possible over over the year over two semesters we approach all Hong Kong schools.
Our public and youth engagement continues, of course, with our summer camp. Over a hundred students with eight artist educators. It's a superb, really a place to encourage our youth to become to think about what it means to be an artist, a designer, an architect into the future. But also our
各位領導、各位同事、各位朋友，非常榮幸，今天上午有機會為大家匯報我們，呃，西九龍表演藝術部門的一些項目。呃，首先，呃，各位應該很熟悉我們西九龍的嘉諾計劃，是三百六十度，We have a three hundred and sixty degree strategy。
要contribute to Hong Kong's arts ecology and arts market, and that's a focus on artists, arts administrators and audience (AAA). So first, I'll talk about our development in capacity building (rencai peiyu) of the artists and the arts administrators. We have been doing a number of years.
Supporting rising stars of Cantonese opera, collaborating with Koshan Theatre, this is both preserving the heritage of Cantonese opera and also innovating for a new century and a new generation of artists to take the art form forward. We are now next year starting the fourth year of an incredibly successful.
Producers Network. This brings together arts administrators and arts producers from the Asia Pacific region for professional exchange and development. And a number of performance collaborations and exchanges have resulted from bringing together producers from different countries to these meetings. And the next one will be in May of next year, the fourth.
Creation for Free Space is a series that we've developed, really positioning West Kowloon as a thought leader in the local and international arts ecology. As you'll see from this, is just a highlighted selection of the projects we've done. Each one in close partnership with local Hong Kong.
藝術組織，Edward Lamb Dance Theatre Manchester International was with Samson Young， whom Sahania just mentioned was at the Venice Biennale。 Hong Kong artists in collaboration with Edinburgh and Auckland artists， as well as Zuni Acasahidron and Theatre du Peuple two theatre organisations locally。 So all of these focus on our。
嗯。
啊，因為時間有限，我先跳過去那個。
We had to leave the theatre, so there's tremendous interest, and this production is invited back to tour China next year.
We have a number of memorandums of understanding. I'm highlighting just this one in particular. It's with.
作為 staff and it's proven to really contribute to both West Kowloon and to their careers. So it's an ongoing programme that we're proud of and will continue.
Well as West Kowloon collaborating with a number of world theatre venues to co-commission his latest work, which has already premiered at Sadler's Wells in London, one of the leading dance centres in the world, and it will be presented in our own Free Space when it opens in 2019.
作為我知，你哋都好熟悉《Free Space》發生。係，佢哋係我哋嘅月度户外節目，免費對觀眾，聚焦於音樂，但亦包括多種其他流派同活動。下一次會喺一月十四號，我哋期待見到你哋喺度。
Simon Says是結果這創意空間來自我們的舞蹈社區，那是一個與香港的Unlock Dancing Plaza和法國的Cécile Dujardin從法國，它在法國首演這部新作品，然後從此巡迴香港和廣東。
另一個成功嘅節目，要高點，係一個兩週嘅節目，喺合作嘅方式，同Swire Properties喺十月、十一月，兩週，八十個本地同海外嘅藝術家，同二十九場表演。我們接管咗整個地產，有劇場、舞蹈、音樂同觀眾嘅合作項目。
Studio Wayne McGregor. Now, I'm sure members here are familiar. Wayne McGregor is one of the leading choreographers not only in the UK but worldwide, having choreographed for opera, ballet, contemporary dance, film and television. His three-year strategy with West Kowloon Performing Arts involves exchanges, workshops, online platforms, as
現在，如我所提，我們的焦點在於培訓藝術家以及藝術管理人員。我們的表演藝術實習計劃有三個入學季節，每個實習持續六個月，我們每年約有三十名實習生，其中不少人都非常有天份，我們保留了他們。
所以那是發展的一些亮點，與藝術家和藝術行政人員有關。就觀眾而言，我們有幾項成功的項目可以高舉。三年的茶室劇場品嚐。現在，如您所知，在西楚中心將會有一個茶室劇場。在這之前，我們已經舉辦了幾場茶室劇場。
表演，和最成功的，有一萬五千八百次的直播觀看。這，你可以想成是，在一個巨大的露天劇場，有萬五千八百名觀眾。所以，這是一個很好的證明，有多少觀眾對射箭感興趣，這預示著射箭中心會開幕。
The experimental Chinese opera series has launched with our own creation of《霸王別姬》，which premiered in Shanghai, also in Hong Kong as part of our series, and was in Beijing last month. With such interest from Beijing, the post-performance discussions often lasted longer than an hour until.
然後最後，highlighting two of our community involvement projects，We Dance，takes place at the Free Space Happening。They're led by local dance partners。In the last year，there have been six events with more than 7，000 participants，all different dance genres，partnerships all with local dance companies leading the。
charge， and the next one will be in January， and you are all welcome to join. And then finally， I want to highlight our 101 lecture and workshop series， which covers all genres. It goes into the schools， partners with different community groups， and it also focuses not only on the Sichu dance， theatre， music genres， but also art criticism.
thank you.
yes.
噉。
Finish.
多謝主席，咁多位議員早晨。嗯。
Arts management and these are all free for the community. So thank you very much. Those are our highlights today.
好，噉啊，而家可以請委員咧就，主席仲有一個補論。O.K. 好，莊女士。
頭先我哋誒剛才藝術總監講咗一啲我哋自家製作嘅誒節目啦。咁呢啲節目將來都會喺我哋嘅表演場地嗰度上演嘅。咁另外一個好重要嘅用家就係租用者。咁嗯，我今日就會同大家講一講呢一個租用者我哋嗰個租用政策嘅。
另外一個我哋好重要嘅主題就係我哋希望幫助香港嘅中小誒嘅藝團啦。咁因為大家都知誒九大之外，其他嘅全部都屬於叫做中小型啦。咁而我哋收費機制係特登降低嘅門檻咧，令到呢一啲嘅中小藝團咧係可以喺文化區度演出嘅。一陣間我會講得更加詳細。
噉我哋嘅藝術場地租用政策咧，其實咧就喺呢一個而家嘅第一期裏邊咧，就適用於我哋嘅戲曲中心啦、啊啊自由空間啦、free space啦，同埋將來嘅Lyric Theatre Complex我哋嘅誒劇場、我嘅theatre誒表演藝術場地嘅。咁而我哋個好重要嘅四大目標咧，第一個咧就係文創造就嘅。
第一樣最緊要嘅嘢就係引導創作咯，因為我哋有我哋嘅場地嘅時候，我哋就希望每一個嘅表演啊藝術者咧，或者一個嘅誒performing company咧，都可以去令到佢哋嘅創作咧係上到佢哋喺佢哋唔同嘅場地裏邊咧係上演佢哋嘅節目嘅。咁另外就係當當然係要增加各樣嘅演出嘅機會啦。
誒培育更多嘅觀眾啦，咁而從而係能夠做到咧，有促進文化嘅欣賞嘅。咁另一個我哋好特別嘅特色咧，就係藝術主導。我哋每一個場地咧有佢獨有獨有嘅藝術使命嘅，由藝術總監咧去決定每一個場地、每一個週期或者每一個星期，甚至無係唔同嘅誒地方有。
唔同嘅時候嘅時候，有佢嗰個藝術嘅定位嘅。譬如話喺戲曲中心，我哋可以有陣時係揀下某一個劇作家啦，又或者係甚至無喺一啲小劇場嚟揀一啲monologue嘅嘅表演嘅。咁藝術團隊會發掘一啲有潛質嘅製作啦，希望佢哋喺文化區嗰度嗰度上演啦，甚至無係上演一啲比較長期嘅時間。
作為一個表演藝術嘅場地，我哋當然要表誒誒保保護呢一個表演啦。噉我哋表演傳頌呢一個嘅誒主題咧，就係希望藝術租用者可以優先預訂我哋嘅場地。另外就係藝藝術租租用者咧，係比較畀嘅租金咧係比較細少一啲嘅。咁而個收費機制咧，我哋而家嘅動。
我哋嘅誒計劃咧係同呢一個票房掛鈎嘅。咁換句話説，你個票房高啲嘅時候，你畀嘅收費就會高啲啦。咁但係其實呢一個機制有一個好大嘅好處嘅，我哋係幫緊一啲中小藝團嘅。咁而收費機制，我哋喺降低咗嗰個誒門檻嘅時候，就支持咗一個長期嘅演出製作。咁而另
咁而呢一個嘅誒場地租用政策，究竟係適用於邊啲地方咧？噉我哋第一個當然係表演藝術場地啦。咁而喺表演藝術場地裏邊咧，藝術同埋非藝術嘅租用者啦，誒去到不同嘅藝術裏邊啦，每一個空間啦，都係喺呢一個藝術政策裏邊，呢個租用政策裏邊誒包含住嘅。咁而喺我哋嘅藝術
Okay.
綜合藝術嘅。
咁誒，非藝術租用者更加簡單啦，唔係以上個所講嘅就係非藝術租用者㗎。
而喺十個月之內咧，就會係所有場地藝術租用者啦，包括呢一個非藝術租用者。
噉我用我用另外一個圖，因為呢啲圖表嚟解釋嘅，我用翻呢個戲曲中心五月嗰個誒時間表啊，誒如果喺
去到十二個月咧，就有仲有啲咩剩餘嘅誒時間表咧？噉就會有其他嘅藝術租用者咧，都會可以上到我哋嘅誒嘅時間表啦。
加一個嘅票房分賬，而唔使飛嗰啲咧就會一個定額嘅比較高嘅定額嘅收費啦。咁而非藝術租用者咧，係需要畀較多嘅租金，即係佢即係話佢哋除咗冇呢一個時間表嗰個誒優勢之外咧，喺個租金方面咧亦都會比較多啲嘅。
公園同埋休憩用地裏邊咧，咁嗰所有嘅藝術租用者，跨不同藝術類別嘅咧，都會受呢一個嘅誒政策去誒監管嘅。咁換句話説，就係如果你租用嗰個地方，我嚟做誒跑步啊、瑜伽啊嗰啲咧，就唔受呢一個嘅政策去誒監管嘅。
咁究竟咩叫藝術租用者咧？其實個誒定義咧喺呢度講得好清楚㗎啦。誒，只要你係做表演藝術嘅，無論你個表演藝術嗰個內容係乜嘢咧，都係喺呢一個藝術租用者。簡單啲講，就算你做電影，如果係一個李後主啊任伯嘅誒電影咧，都屬於係藝術租用者。
時間表而去由藝術總監旗下嘅藝術團隊咧去選擇佢邊一個可以上到我哋嘅talent，譬如話而家紫色嗰啲咧，我哋當佢哋噉樣上咗啦。咁去到四二零一八年嘅四月啦，就會係其他嘅藝術追夢者啦。咁而喺戲曲中心嚟講咧，戲曲嘅節目依然有一個優先嘅誒優次嘅次序嘅。
咁其實一個藝術個我哋嘅場地租用政策最緊要其實得兩樣嘢嘅，一就係時間表，同埋我今年收費嗰個機制。咁下邊我就講一講我哋嘅時間表。時間表我哋其實我哋希望能夠誒做到咧係誒efficient嘅，咁所以我哋係集中喺我哋嘅誒營運組集中去處理呢一個所。
所有嘅誒租用者嘅application噉，而我哋會接受三年前嘅預訂。咁即係話，大家有構思到想做一個節目嘅時候咧，就已經可以嚟訂場㗎啦。訂場係冇任何嘅嗯合約去去幫住大家嘅合約嘅模式就會喺由我哋由十八個月前開始去同大家去。
誒落實嗰張合約喺十八個月前，喺文化區管理局或者駐場嘅藝團咧係有優先誒上去呢一個嗯個時間表嘅權利嘅。咁而十六個月前咧就會係場地所屬嘅藝術類別啦。換句話説，用翻戲劇中心嚟做誒例子嘅話，戲曲嘅節目喺十六。
個月前就可以優先上去我哋所有嘅誒戲曲中心裏邊嘅場地嘅租用，而喺十四個月前咧就係牽涉到其他嘅藝術類別啦。噉我哋喺文化區嚟講分嘅咧就係五個總共五個藝術類別嘅，就有戲曲啦、音樂（music）、誒dance舞蹈、theatre戲劇同埋variety嘅。
好唔該曬。
噉啊！
咁整個誒。
噉我今日嘅presentation係咁多，唔該。
個場地其實係畀曬其他飛戲戲曲嘅用家嘅。
噉啊，而家咧就開放畀委員提問嘅。
咁另外就係好緊要嘅，就係年度財度財務目標啦。我哋係需要平衡翻藝術同埋呢一個財政上嘅需要嘅。
但係，如果你誒細心去計一計呢條數咧，就係將你個當你個票房收入越嚟越高嘅時候，其實你所佔嗰個個percentage嗰個百分比咧係越嚟越低嘅。
誒每個活動空間嘅使用率啦，究竟有冇用盡嗰個誒場地嘅有嘅時間啦？咁同埋個租用者嘅滿意程度啦，我哋唔希望話租用者係有誒對我哋嘅服務啊各樣嘢有有誒有啲不滿嘅，我哋希望能夠做到佢哋嘅滿意嘅。
推之啊，去到比較呢一個右邊最盡嗰度五十萬嘅誒票房收入嘅話，我哋就有四萬蚊嘅票房分獎啦，再加本來嗰個base嘅四萬四千蚊，就係八萬四千蚊嘅。換句話説，當你嘅票房高啲嘅時候，你嗰個嘅我哋嘅嗰個收入就會高啲，佢哋畀緊個錢就會高啲咯。咁
呢一個十二月嘅時候咧，喺二零一七年十二月嘅時候咧，就喺西九文化區本身嘅節目咧，就可以首先上呢一個嘅五月嘅二零一九年五月嘅節目。呢一個calendar係二零一九年五月嘅。咁當時間一路推進嘅時候，去到二零一八年嘅二月，我哋就會睇曬所有戲曲嘅租用者佢哋想用嘅時。
咁下一個我想講嘅咧就係我哋嘅收費機制。其實收費機制咧，我哋係分翻藝術租用者啦，同埋非藝術租用者嘅藝術租用者分兩種，一個就係畀非入場嘅節目啦，或者係唔需要飛或者係by invitation嗰啲啦，即係譬如受邀請嗰啲啦。咁誒憑票入場嘅節目咧，我哋會收個基本收費。
噉我哋亦都畀一個例子，大家譬如誒左手邊個個軸咧，就係呢一個我哋場地收用嘅誒租用嘅收費啦。而下低嗰個咧就係我哋嘅誒總票房嘅收入，誒每一個租用者嘅總票房收入。譬如話，我哋而家個市價係六萬蚊噉樣樣租一日啦，八個小時啦。
我哋會特登係降低個門檻，去到四萬四千蚊加呢一個八個percent個總票房收入嘅八個percent嘅。咁誒，大家可以睇到就係，譬如你個票房只係得十萬嘅，我當一千位，你平均嗰個係一百蚊嘅嘅票嘅票價嘅話咧，噉我哋嘅收費就會五萬二千蚊咯。咁如此類。
誒整個租用政策咧，我哋有一個完善嘅成效量度咧，去計翻我哋究竟個PPI做唔做得到啦。咁其中一個就係最重要嘅，就係我哋嘅節目類型，究竟個比例係咪能夠反反映翻我哋嗰個藝術定位嘅？換句話説，就係戲曲中心，你係咪做翻比較多嘅戲曲咧？唔係話將誒個。
Like a hundred thousand children this year.
即係我好希望見到係你哋有多一啲合作。
誒，而你幫到佢哋之後，佢哋可以幫啲學生。
誒連問連答，誒四分鐘先啦，好嘛？
咧去嗰度，可以畀佢哋認識一啲過去冇乜機會接觸嘅嘢。
其實五分鐘都得嘅，我哋而家嘅人數唔緊要。啊，黃碧雲啊，議員。
係啦，其實呢啲誒好多program咧，其實而家唔需要等到啲硬件起曬都做到。我見到你都試緊好多嘢。
噉我希望可以見到呢啲噉樣嘅summer program啦，同埋呢啲誒同學校裏邊嗰個嘅合作。
咁嗰班嘅藝術工作者點樣可以benefit，即係可以從你西九而家做緊嘅工作得益？
咁又或者你哋同學校嘅誒藝術嘅老師一齊合作，去帶動啲年青人係認識藝術、關注藝術。噉我我相信噉樣咧，就係話。
誒，我特別希望你哋咧，就係誒可以講多啲咧，點樣同而家啲中小學啦、大學，因為喺中小學、大學裏邊其實都有一啲係做藝術教育嘅工作者，又有好多學生，噉佢哋係需要。
咁而西九藝術場地對於我哋整個文化產業鏈嘅承諾咧，其實喺文化產業裏邊喺三大嗰個比較重要嘅一環咧，就係由呢個表演團體去到呢一個誒演出經紀公司做嘅推廣啊、業務啊同埋後勤嘅支援啦。咁去到一個場地嘅正式嘅演出嘅，咁喺我哋呢一個嘅誒。
政策裏邊咧，我哋接受三年前預訂就已經保障咗佢哋喺創作嗰個嘅誒氛圍或者係創作嗰個空間啦。咁另外，我哋喺成個啊藝術政策裏邊，藝術中型者優先啦，同埋藝術中型者有呢個價錢優惠啦。咁而我哋支持比較長期嘅演出製作咯，噉就希望個收費機制咧係分擔咗。
咗佢哋嗰個嘅誒資金流嘅嘅壓力啦，同埋都幫助中小藝團可以去到文化區嘅演出。咁而最後喺表演場地方面，我哋嘅營運小組咧係會用呢一個服務為先，同埋依一個優質服務咧去服務我哋所有嘅租用者啦、觀眾啦，同埋以至嚟到文化區嘅每一位嘅賓客嘅。
誒多謝主席，同埋多謝西九管理局咁多同事誒介紹你哋工作啦。噉我都見到你哋都花咗好多心思嘅。噉我咧就係誒比較關心就係即係你哋有咁多專家啦，又會有好多啲international嘅artist過嚟啦。噉我我想問咧就係。
你哋嘅人數誒多極都唔夠喺學校裏邊，可能每間校都有一位老師，咁可能都有一千幾百，我唔知有幾多人啊呢一個嘅community。噉我希望你哋可以喺呢啲硬件未起好曬之前咧，盡快做好呢一度咧，係等學校嗰度嘅誒藝術教官。
作者提升佢哋，亦都等佢哋好熟悉西九做緊啲咩嘢。噉我希望呢一度你哋可唔可以講多啲你哋嗰啲計劃，譬如誒，即係從教師個角度係噉樣樣啦，學校啦，另一邊就係家長啦，佢哋可能暑假係好希望咧，啲小朋友都去學啲嘢啊，噉佢哋。
都會，但係佢哋就會去叫佢學興趣班啊、陶瓷啊、畫畫啊咩啊噉。咁其實有冇一啲西九管理局？其實你哋都可以諗到一啲program咧summer嘅，係等多啲即係做旺你個場，即係做做旺你嗰個嘅品牌，係等啲家長都知道哦。其實原來最正。
好，啊，Patrick Cosyns啊，Patrick Cosyns啊，Thank you, Mr. Chairman. In fact, this is a very important part of our approach at this stage. We we we touched on a lot of the education programmes that we run. For example, M Plus takes their M Plus Rover out to schools. I think we've reached over something.
好，噉啊。
to them the the fantastic artwork because again young people have to be a major target for this.
On top of that, we also have a series of programmes we call the 101 series, which is open to everybody, but it's simple introduction.
踎貼牌，然後去到嗰個community嗰度，咁所以我我希望咧，你你哋有一啲做得好嘅咧，可以深入啲，再做大啲，噉係等多啲人可以受惠咯。
嗰啲咧，其實可以大做做多啲，因為你如果做一個好嘅program，但係轉轉香港，你得一百個人可以參加，其實就冇乜impact。即係我哋咁多嘅學生，咁所以邊一啲做得好嗰啲咧，係要有replication。
Through this outreach programme, we work already with educators in the schools, the teachers. So we we give them teaching packs so that they can help us to teach the children as well as the resident artists. That's one example. Another example is where, for Free Space, for example, we run programmes for children. In fact.
Fact coming up on the 14th of January, we will have Oh My Kids running educational programmes in the Free Space event day. On top of that, we've again in the presentation touched on our summer education programme run by M+. We have 100 children.
In that case, but this is the third year that we've done that, so that's over 300 children, some of whom we're now looking how can we encourage them to become alumni going forward. I think you've touched on a very important point, which is educating the educators, and again, that's an area where, for example, in Siu, we've
Been talking to people because it's important that we get young people to come in. Another example for the M Plus Pavilion. Every show we bring groups of young people, children from schools, in as tour groups, and we take our our curators and show them round, explain what they see, introduce.
On top of that, we also run similar programmes for dance, for theatre, for music, and indeed in the music field, we've been able to introduce new forms of music to younger people. So we have a very active programme in this area, and I think it's something that we can continue to build on.
它旨在讓年輕人和對不同藝術形式感興趣的人來到這裡接受這些藝術形式的教育。我還能説下去，但我認為你已經有印象了。主席，主席，我我相信西九邊試過好多program，噉我相信有一啲如果你覺得好成功。
陳淑莊副主席，好多謝主席。其實就兩邊問題嘅噉啊。首先誒，方迎誒歡迎啊，方女士，即係呢個係啊Miss Freeman咧，就即係加入啊西九大家庭。雖然我唔係西九嘅一份子啦，咁但係但係佢入嚟咧都唔容易嘅啊，即係有啲風雨嘅。咁咧就啊，但係我對佢有期望嘅。因
因為誒，反而我覺得佢嘅背景咧，反而令到佢咧能夠協助西九咧喺誒呢一個地點，可以做一個比較即係國際性啲嘅，但係又尊重翻誒香港特有文化嘅嗰種噉樣嘅定位。咁所以反而我係對有期望嘅，咁亦都希望佢即係可以。
以揾到個方法去融合，同埋更加可以放大咗誒香港嘅呢一個特殊嘅位置。咁咧就誒，但係咧都要問下問題嘅。咁咧就誒，第一啦，咁咧就誒，我想問下之前嘅風波誒處理咗未？咁咧雖然咧，我見到咧就誒後邊有一個誒表，就係呢一個。
個誒戲曲中心顧問小組嘅成員名單咁咧，就誒都見到即係誒有一啲誒好有份量嘅人喺裏面噉，就想睇下誒之前所關注嘅嘢有冇辦法處理得到噉，同埋誒誒會唔會即係誒即係對之後有冇影響啦？第二咧就係關於嗰個誒實。
即係而家仲係計劃當中咧，啊唔該，主席。
Coordination with the different sectors, which I think is important.
好啊，誒，關於頭先嘅問題比較多係同場地租用有關，我請阿Lisa整體噉樣答一答。
six months, we look for nine months as a as a possibility even a year. So that I think is is going to be worthwhile. But we've also introduced these overseas internship opportunities for people.
Suhani was talking about the Venice Biennale, which is further extending the programme. Can we cooperate with local groups? Yes, I mean we're already cooperating with the universities, so that's something we will do. Louis, why don't you talk about the other questions?
實習生計劃啦，咁咧就我睇過咧，就誒秘書處為我哋準備嘅文件。其實以往咧都知道係由本來三個月至六個月，咁已經提升到六個月。咁但係講到咁好咧，會唔會再長啲咧？因為政府嗰啲即係所搞嘅，即係康文署嗰個都比較長少少。係咪你哋有啲crossover啊，定係會有聯係嘅咧？
咁呢個我想了解，同埋咧嗰個誒誒嗰個誒誒租場嗰個計劃咧，我可能晏少少再問我聽，我呢兩個先好嘛？唔該曬，主席。好，噉啊，柏志高先生。
好啊！誒唔該曬誒主席誒，我哋同誒藝術業界嘅關係咧，其實係過去咁多年咧，一路係唔停噉樣喺度溝通緊。咁喺過去嗰三個月裏邊，我哋一路都有同誒誒誒戲曲業界啦、百和會館咧，一路有唔同嘅接觸嘅。噉我哋誒嚟緊咧係策劃緊一啲。
啲誒新嘅項目或者係新嘅節目，噉係令到我哋可以強化同誒戲曲業界嗰個關係。噉我亦都會翻翻去我哋頭先所講嘅誒戲曲中心顧問小組裏邊，藉住呢個顧問小組嘅功能咧，誒喺裏邊咧就係向我哋誒西九嘅管誒誒董事局咧就係確認或者係。
誒，我哋將來同誒戲曲嘅節目係點樣樣噉，所以咧嚟緊，我哋會一路係同業界嚟到溝通咧。誒，同埋我哋會有新嘅節目會跟住會推出嘅。好誒，咁另好。
Thank you。誒，咁另外，主席，我仲想追問下關於即係第五十六七段咧，即係關於佢哋嗰個租場。噉啊，特別咧係誒就住第五十五段咧，就係講誒支持較長期演出製作。我知道其實呢一樣嘢咧，都係即係呢一個可以能夠誒有個長期嘅演出嘅嘅場地咧，其實都係西九。
其中一個誒出現嘅原因嚟嘅，因為佢當年係董建華年代嘅時候，即係佢覺得誒點解外國嘅地方就可以有一個咁長期嘅演出誒場地？點解香港係冇冇啲噉樣嘅機會咧？咁噉，我就想問下誒你哋具體係點樣去支持呢個較長期嘅演出製作？因為呢個係。
係其中一個誒，你哋嘅誒，即係一個原則啦。另外就係嗰個誒，關於嗰個門票嗰個啦，即係譬如話，我就我一路都對嗰個茶館好有興趣嘅，大家都知㗎啦。咁即係有冇個大概幾錢到？即係同埋，因為我自己都出去租過場啦。我見到你哋呢一個收費嘅模式咧，似乎有少少唔同嘅，因為。
譬如話，我去誒誒藝術中心嗰度誒租場咧，咁都係即係門票係唔會瓜分嘅嘛。即係主要你交咗租場，咁門票就誒畀少少誒康文處。如果幫我哋買飛嘅話，咁跟住其他嗰啲就我哋嘅收入。噉我就想再具體瞭解下，即係大約你哋諗住定定個租金有冇得？即係我哋瞭解一下，或
誒，我首先誒誒誒，多謝你嘅提問啊。但係個價錢，我哋暫時唔講得住，係啦。我哋因為仲要過呢一個嘅董事局嘅財政財務預算噉，所以過咗誒未來嗰幾個月，我哋就可以去向外公佈㗎啦。噉啊，關於你頭先所講話長長期嘅演出啦，咁其實我哋支持長期嘅演出咧，唔係話淨係。
係純粹諗一啲音樂劇三個禮拜、兩個禮拜嗰啲節目嘅，咁甚至乎我哋一啲中小藝團做緊三日嘅節目，可唔可以做到四日咧？噉我哋嗰個收費機制，特意降低個門檻咧，我哋淨係收咗個 baseline，咁令到佢哋有一個無論你個門票，因為其實有陣時佢做開三日，做第四日其實有風險嘅。咁呢個風險係誒文化區係願意。
而承擔嘅噉，所以喺呢一個承擔佢哋嗰個誒製作嗰個費用啦，同埋嗰個誒做多一日，因為有各樣嘅演出嘅費用嘅時候，我哋係願意承擔呢一個，令到佢哋可以做多一日咯。咁頭先你所講嘅兩至三個星期嗰類嘅節目咧，我哋就會誒當我哋收集曬所有嘅application嘅時候。
Thank you.
Patrick Cosyns, I'll ask Alison to answer this one. But in fact, just to remind members, we did cover a lot of this in the presentation earlier. So, Alison.
個互動方面提升香港藝藝藝術嘅水平，如果有嘅話咧，個比例每年大約幾多度？咁誒，另另外預算方面有冇呢方面嘅預算咧？第一個問題先。
葉小玲議員，誒多謝主席。誒就睇到文件咧，即係將來我哋誒西九文化區咧，將會成為世界級嘅文化藝術樞紐。嚇，呢個係我哋嘅遠景啦。
Organised through CPAA中央演出公司，which is under the Ministry of Culture， and our Shichu Centre is very focused on collaborating with networks and partners to bring in Shichu organisations to perform at the Shichu Centre. So our that's a summary of some of our strategies.
就會集中嚟睇下，究竟我哋希望揀啲乜嘢喺我哋嘅文化區度上演啦。咁呢一樣嘢，我就會由我哋嘅營運組同埋咧藝術團隊咧一齊去決定嘅。咁而當然喺中間裏邊一定唔多唔少，我哋會有一啲嘅啊啊想法啊，或者有唔同嘅計算嘅方法啊，或者有唔同嘅啊啊preference。
咁而我哋誒有一個嘅好重要嘅嘢，就係藝術主導。所以誒，換句話説咧，就係喺呢一個藝術團隊最後決定，無論任何一個誒租用者，無論任何一個時段，都係最後咧由呢個藝術團隊去決定嘅。好，主席有冇其他人問排隊問啊？阿姚思榮議員，哦，好好好，好，阿。
咁誒，但係睇翻咧誒，我哋好多時都係好誒講本地嘅藝術團體嘅發展。咁按照我哋目前嘅藝術團體發展咧，誒具唔具備條件達到即係未來嘅軟件誒軟景？如果係誒即係條件不足嘅話，我哋未來有咩嘢工作？
能夠提升達到呢個目標咧，噉樣喺呢個過程入面，誒，我唔知道誒西九文化區喺呢個過渡期入面，每年有冇個預算係邀請一啲世界知名嘅或者係國內知名嘅團體嚟香港表演，啊，咁使到呢個。
它係一個重要優先事項，為我們聚焦於本地以及國際。我認為，一丁兩條腿，少一萬天朝。在平衡和比例方面，我們的優先事項在於首先聚焦於支持和展示香港團體。
然後，local Asia region， and then international。 in terms of how we present it， the team has been focused on partnerships over the last number of years， and this was both for practical strategic reasons as well as content reasons。 we have a number of
MOUs with Australia, the UK, Finland and other countries in Europe and Asia, which allows us to share resources to bring artists in both directions. This allows professional sharing for artists to potentially collaborate and learn.
作為允許我們機會，呈現一些世界最佳的製作，從世界各地在我們的舞台上，與合作組織，例如澳洲藝術委員會、各大使館和夥伴關係。而這也意味著我們不僅僅呈現這些。
世界級 productions here in Hong Kong. It means that those arts organisations and countries are paying attention to Hong Kong artists, and in turn will invite them to their festivals, venues, studios in in turn. So that it's a two-way street. The other way that we are developing.
啊，冇嘢。
Mr. Chairman, if Sir Hanu can answer that one, please.
個誒專業服務啊，做得更加好一啲咧。
噉啊，到到我先問問啦，跟住就。
The tour guides are aware of that. That's something we're looking at at the moment.
Mr. Chairman, if I can just pick up on the tourism angle, in fact we we are in.
We're still working on the budgets for the for the next three years, but that will be presented to members I think in February. So members will have the opportunity to look at that.
導師和培訓，如果他們有興趣，所以它係一個非常重要的部分，係我們做嘅。而正如我早前喺我嘅講述中提到，合作同夥伴關係係M+嘅一個核心使命。
這些partnerships是通過MOUs與中華人民共和國。Lewis和我剛剛從一個會議與Duncan一起簽署了一個MOU，與新的絲綢之路劇場網絡，這是一個由來自超過44個國家的劇場和藝術機構組成的網絡。
好，誒頭先我問係有冇啲誒一個就每年嘅比例啦，同埋個預算有幾多喺呢方面誒作出即係開支或者收入呢個比例預算嚇。Mr. Chairman，嗯，I I can confirm we do have a budget for this for every year. It forms part of the performing arts budget. Um, obviously.
第第二個問題咧，就係有關誒導賞安排啊。噉我都好高興，你哋誒已經開始誒培訓啲導賞誒員啦嚇，有一百人。咁誒未來誒當西九開放之後咧，誒你哋最終能夠有幾多專職或者兼職嘅導賞員？咁誒？
另外咧，你知啦，好導賞啦，好多旅行團嚟到誒西九參觀，咁呢啲導賞員足唔足夠應付？如果唔足夠嘅話，會唔會考慮同旅行社合作培訓香港一啲嘅導遊咧？噉佢哋可以有一個資格去誒協助導賞，咁使到成個西九文化嘅。
For your question, docents are a central part of museum work, and we've begun with our first one hundred and five docents. Now, they are they will grow as we become a major museum. There's no question that we need to develop that arm of what we do, and many of those doc.
it's it's their volunteers and it depends on their time how much they give to us and we work around that program it's something that we're also partnering with our L C S D colleagues in terms of the training we have opened it up for our colleagues in the L C S D museums to attend.
好。
Louis， can you deal with the other ones?
噉啊，仲有少少時間咧，我都想問呢個。
Mr. Chairman, let me deal with the first one. The publicity, we do actually do a lot of publicity.
噉佢哋係咪都喺即係喺粵劇界裏面有繼續一個發展啦？咁最後就係誒頭先介紹嘅都係。
communications and and media handling, so for example when we were at the the Silk Road event recently, we did pick up some publicity for that, so we it tends to be programmatic.
二零一七年可能去到十二月，即係嘅計劃或者之前嗰啲咁嚟緊。二零一八或者即係未來有冇啲咩即係發展咁可以話畀我哋聽下咧？三個問題嘅啫。
即係除咗戲曲之外，其他嘅音樂、舞蹈同埋戲劇嘅我哋一啲誒，無論係新嘅人才同埋新嘅場地咧，都會係一係一九年出現。咁所以我相信喺二零一八同埋一九年咧，係我哋戲誒西九咁多年之後嘅一個開幕年嘅。
誒租金機制啊，咁租金機制頭先介紹咗一個比較新嘅機制啦，咁亦都用咗個例子啦。咁個基本收費同埋即係票房分賬，我想問下咧，咁其實個基本收費咧係咪已經係可以即係等同個啊場地經營嘅成本嘅咧？我想問下。
即係例如佢六萬蚊嗰度，噉佢你就收四萬幾，咁四萬幾係咪嗰度？會唔會其實我就想問，如果嗰個即係真係佢當然嗰啲中小型劇團嘅票房一般理想嘅時候，會唔會連埋即係西九都要蝕蝕埋嗰個成本咧？自己都。
constant communication with the tourism board on a number of different issues, because clearly it is important for us that we spread the message about West Kaluan Cultural District both regionally and internationally. In so far as you know, explaining and introducing what we're doing, so that
噉啊，我就想即係都問下啦。咁其實即係都見得到過去都做咗唔少工作。咁誒，我都想問下，其實呢啲工作嘅宣傳，即係誒，即係因為其實都做咗唔少。咁但係我就想睇翻，即係其實個宣傳效果係點？因為其實誒，如果唔係睇報告咧，可能我都真係未必知道咧。其實西九做咗噉。
多嘢嘅呢個第一點，第二點咧就係過去咧都見得到有啲人才培訓啦，例如即係啊西即係粵劇個新星啊嗰啲啦。咁有冇做一啲嘅追蹤咧？佢哋參加完呢個新星即係之後咧，噉佢哋而家個發展係點樣嘅咧？咪都辦咗即係幾年嘅啦。
For programming, it tends to be targeted at the audiences that are likely to be interested. In terms of general publicity about the district, we do get a lot of coverage, often because of attending at ledger meetings. Some of the best publicity we get, not necessarily good publicity, but the best. We also use all of the.
Different internet and multimedia channels, because frankly nowadays for younger people that's the best way to communicate with them. But we don't forget the traditional media, so we do have contacts both internationally and locally. We've appointed a company to help us with our international.
好，誒我可以答誒第二個問題同埋第三個問題，就關於誒人才培訓同埋嚟緊一八年會做緊啲乜嘢？誒可以咁講，誒我哋過去六年做咗頭先你聽到嘅唔同嘅工作嘅內容，都係為咗等我哋誒新嘅場地喺成立嘅時候、開幕嘅時候，可以無論係誒硬。
In whatever manner.
喺文化中心。
And is this the sort of things that you're going to keep on doing?
And the third thing is your catalogue of achievements. You mention this.
Across the whole district, that's the reality. That sorry, what what millions again? Tens of hundreds.
Can you assure us that fringe artists in Hong Kong will be taken into account as well?
先嗰個即係起碼燈油火，即係唔係賺錢咁燈油火蠟係咪都可以？即係呢啲經營嘅成本都會，即係個基本收費嗰度係擺咗落去嘅啫。係啦，噉啊好啊，莫曼正議員。
Having said that, as we've already indicated in the introduction, there will be reduced charges for artistic groups because that's the priority. So it's that balancing act, and perhaps Lisa can explain the logic behind that.
件方面會有一個新嘅面貌畀到香港市民大眾咧，同埋喺嗰個人才同埋內容嗰方面咧都可以同步咁配合嘅。咁二零一八年底嘅時候咧，戲曲中心咧就會正式開幕㗎啦。咁喺戲曲中心開幕嘅時候咧，大家會見得到我哋嗰幾年過去呢幾年培養嘅新秀同埋誒同粵劇界一齊。
培養嘅新秀同埋新星咧，都會喺誒戲曲中心呢個斬新嘅一個舞台嗰度可以呈現得到。噉我哋誒除咗戲曲中心嘅開幕之後咧之外咧，喺陣間第二個環節裏邊，大家都會見知得到咧，就二零一八年底同埋二零一九年初咧，我哋第二個場地自由空間咧都會陸續咁開幕，意思。
Mr. Chairman, let me start the answer to that question. Then I'll ask Lisa to supplement. Arts venues generally don't make a profit, and the board has accepted that fact. So we're not trying to make a profit out of this operation, but we would try as far as possible to break even if we can.
多謝主席，你嘅提問。嗯，其實我哋嗰個收費機制咧，嗯喺嗰個誒，我哋計算我哋嘅成本嘅時候咧，起碼能夠cover到一啲誒增加咗嘅成本，即係話電費啦，誒一啲誒嚟嚟誒， usher啦，你唔係票務員啦，嗯，同埋誒收收費嗰啲咧，同埋呢一個誒清。
嘅，希望我哋希起碼希望我哋嗰個場地咧能夠啊能夠支援到一啲daily expense咯，但係你話長遠嗰個嘅啊整體嗰個個場地本身嗰個成本咧係實非常之咁高嘅，無論喺嗰個building嗰個方面啦，喺嗰個我哋所有喺度翻工嘅同事啦，去管理翻嗰。
個場地嗰個啲同事咯，咁其實嗰個成本咧，就正如頭先登勤所講咧，係冇可能能夠喺嗰個租務票務嗰度，租務嗰度咧係cover得到嘅，仲要靠好多其他嘅誒收入嘅來源咧，能去令到文化區本身嗰個嘅啊財政咧係能夠比較健康。唔係我理解，所以我都即係誒，好似啊，即係柏治嗰。
There's a question about budget, and they were saying that they will tell in February. I was just wondering, can't you not give us a rough idea about the range? We're talking about millions or tens of millions of.
主席就誒。
噉啊，黃碧雲議員第二輪嘅三分鐘。
給我們一個粗數。我唔係要去做呢個，直到董事會批准。
嗰度嘅問題啦，咁租場嗰度我都同意你呢條定嘅四個原則嘅，即係喺PowerPoint嗰度。
關於嗰個嘅場租場嗰度啲收費同埋嗰啲門券。
public as we possibly can， so these are ongoing pedagogic platforms for that M+ does as a matter of course。
Okay. On the second and third, the fringe artist, I'll defer to Alison and Lewis on the fringe artist and Suhani on the IMP item.
that currently we we only have one facility that's actually operational. That's the M+ pavilion. As we start to move into our own facilities, of course, then it becomes a focus for our
教育和和其他Programming， and it becomes a little bit easier to publicise those events because they become regular within the institution. At the moment, we're camping, and that's part of the challenge that we face.
more independent, more fringe, and on a personal note, my own background in in mainland China was really about discovering the the quote unquote fringe or undiscovered artists and providing resources. And I'm really excited to work with the team to do that here in Hong Kong.
那係我第一個問題，另一個問題係，你似乎聚焦於傳統的、已確立的藝術家在香港。我講的是國際交流界。
M Plus Forum on IM Pay, that's fine. But I must confess, I didn't even know about it. It seems to be very sort of exclusive, right? And this sort of event could have been held anywhere in Hong Kong—the city hall, the art centre, and so on and so forth.
That's my third question. Thank you. Let me deal with the first one. The reason I can't give you the budget obviously is it has to go through the board process. It has to be approved by the various subcommittees, and we're still going through that process. But I can assure you, it is tens, if not hundreds of millions of dollars that we're talking about on an annual basis.
under up to hundreds, hundreds of millions. Of course, we're talking about a major infrastructure development. If you include all of the expenditure on construction, etc., must be. Well, constructions included as well. That's a total budget. Okay, hundreds of millions we're talking about. You can't.
要respond， thank you for your question. And absolutely, in the short answer is yes, absolutely. We're looking not just at established or the big nine. It's an and not or. We need to focus on all levels of the artistic ecology here in Hong Kong, and that's already started through our team heads in dance theatre.
或者習俗和音樂，他們有在花時間，連結與不同的藝術圈層，並包括他們在許多MOUs中，我提到的交流。許多參與這些工作坊和交流的藝術家，並非屬於較為固定的團體。
Okay, thank you. And what about the IMPE event? I will answer that. So IMPE was a multi-partnership between the Graduate School of Design in Harvard in the US and then Hong Kong University here and M Plus, and there were four scholars.
Policy Research Programme. It was open to anybody who wanted to attend in Boston and at Hong Kong U. Very well attended. But we also do M Plus Matters in various forums at Asia Society, at Poly University, wherever those venues are available. We make it a
好。
團雖然你話係都希望可以幫佢哋嘅，即係等佢租得起嗰啲場。即係我希望你真係有啲唔同嘅價錢，係令到嗰啲中小微。
或者獨誒，或者獨立嘅藝術家、個人藝術家，或者真係好細嘅話咧，我哋會主動做一啲噉樣呢方面嘅邀請。咁但係一啲小型嘅團體嘅租用嗰方面嘅安排咧，我交畀阿Lisa同我哋講一講。
Mr. Chetty, going on with the ticketing issue first. Obviously, ticketing will depend on the programme. Some programmes will have different prices depending on the nature of the programme. As far as our own programmes are concerned, the ones that we will
put put on and and work with in conjunction with other organisations. Yes, there will be concessionary tickets. And in fact, for our rising stars programmes, we already have instituted that approach. But for private hire, that's obviously not something we can control. But as far as ours are, yes, definitely. Lisa Babs can comment on the the rest of.
You actually use the word pedagogic. Yes, yes, education for in that in the in the broader sense. Okay, I I just got a rather worry that things might be rather prescribed. Anyway, okay, that somebody else is. Yeah, can I just add a couple of points? It's important to realise.
誒，譬如藝術租用者可以優先誒預訂啊，藝術租用者付較少嘅租金啊，攤分嗰個誒票房嗰個嘅誒風險啊，等等。咁誒，我想問咧，就係誒有兩個問題啦。第一就係咧，嗰啲中小藝。
藝術團體誒，佢唔會即係望門輕嘆啫。我根本都比唔起呢個場租，根本用唔到呢啲場地。因為對啲中小微型嘅藝術團體咧，佢哋係最需要呢啲場地。咁所以如果你唔你你唔能夠defence呢啲噉樣嘅級別，畀到一個佢哋真係進到場。
租到場可以做到表演咧，噉我哋就即係變咗係有一個好靚嘅誒好多嘅噉樣嘅誒場地，但係就可能係丟空嘅時間多過真係用到，咁所以我諗即係呢度係需要有好多心思諗下點樣做，因為我哋唔希望啲場地成日都丟空，我哋希望。
佢係真係好好經常可以使用到。咁第二個咧就係誒嗱，雖然嗰個票價咧可能就會係嗰個租用團體佢會去定，但係我都希望諗下咧，就係話我哋會唔會係應該都要有一啲student ticket或者啲senior，即係話啲誒長者啊退。
退休嘅人士啊，學生啊，佢哋喺嗰個票價上面，佢都慶祝有一個好優惠嘅價錢，即係令到係有錢嘅人、冇錢嘅人，佢哋都可以嚟到睇呢啲噉嘅節目。咁但係呢度似乎我哋就睇唔到你今日present嘅時候有呢啲噉樣嘅資料。噉我第二個咧就係話，你哋講係affordable嘅嗰個。
嗯。
Thank you.
係啊。
都係食落去食得。
Thank you, and I will stick to one language so as not to confuse the translators. Thank you for that reminder. Thank you very much. Thank you. Of course, for your devotion.
掛緊西九，我哋呢個整體，我覺得我哋只要有個政策。我啱啱見到今日兩沓都咁厚嘅時候咧，就就真係都都順手啦。因為尋日我哋啱啱開完呢個環境事務委員會嘅嘅會議，噉我怕小高先生唔好覺得我唔係我唔係所有嘢都執住西九嘅嚇。
講咧都係一個非常重要嘅職位，係為嗰個表演嘅場地定立一個藝術嘅方向。而要呈現個藝術方向咧，最重要嘅咧就係自己嘅製作或者係自己主動邀請嘅一啲節目。噉我跟住請啊Alison可以再elaborate下佢作為一個藝術總監喺呢方面嘅諗法係點樣樣。
個租金，但係我哋因為睇唔到具體嘅數字，究竟compare with康文署而家嘅場地或者其他嘅表演場地，究竟你係會比佢哋一樣啊，低啲啦，抑或係高好多咧？咁咁有冇呢啲噉嘅比較嘅數字？等我哋知道大概西九即係打算係點樣做。
誒主席，誒喺我交畀阿Lisa再講下一啲誒對中小團嚟講喺租用嘅方面安排之誒之前咧，我想提一提咧喺個節目安排上咧，其實我哋都係兩條腿走走路。一方面咧，我哋會主動邀請一啲團體做一啲藝術上嘅合作，對一啲誒個別嘅誒藝術家。
係誒，多謝主席，多謝你嘅提問。咁其實中小藝團咧，其實我哋嘅場地裏邊咧有好多中小型嘅劇場嘅咁誒，亦都好似啲誒歌星咁先算啦。佢哋好多時都係喺翻一啲比較細嘅場地演出，係秘科佢哋能夠去到呢個紅館嘅演出。咁但係用一個同一個道理咧，其實喺我哋嘅場地，我哋有一啲嘅。
誒open air嘅場地咧，一啲誒户外嘅場地咧，亦都有啲小型嘅劇場啦。咁從而咧去到一個千零人嘅劇場咧，噉就係希望大家增加佢哋嘅唔同嘅演出機會，亦都係唔同嘅場次、唔同嘅場地裏邊咧，去令到佢哋嗰個嗰個嘅藝術嘅水平咧一路去提升嘅。咁而頭先問到關啲定價嘅問題啦，其實我哋係要。
要同翻市場掛鈎嘅，我哋不不可能話進入個市場嘅時候用一個太高嘅價錢啦。因為外國用嘅方式咧，亦都唔同啦。咁但係香港亦都有佢獨特嘅模式啦。咁所以我哋喺我哋考慮嗰個定價嗰時候咧，亦都係睇翻香港本身嗰個市場嗰個定位喺邊度啦，同埋大家本身嗰個營售力嘅能力係有去到邊度啦，包括嗰個票價啦。咁所以喺
我哋嗰個定價裏邊咧，我哋係考慮曬所有嘅誒嘅可能性啦，去定翻我哋嗰個誒嘅水平咯。噉啊，朱姐，其實我就係想問就係話，你做咗market research，即係知道市價大概點。而家我想問嘅就係西九嘅定位，你會比個market price高一啲啊，定還是低一啲，定係我未？
聽係個market price啊，簡短答啊嘛。係多謝主席。咁其實喺頭先我個present中入邊亦都提到嘅，就算譬如話喺頭先我其中一張嘅誒slide裏邊咧，就係講到譬如嗰個市場嘅定價係個水平大概係六萬蚊噉樣樣先算啦。我哋係會特登撳翻低佢去到四萬四千蚊加八嘅percent。噉我哋撳。
減低咗個水平，就令到一啲中小藝團嗰個壓力冇咁大啦。咁另外，因為我哋另外嗰八個percent係同嗰個票房掛鈎啦，無論佢票房做到幾多，我哋都係只係攞一個誒比較即係八個percent嘅percentage啦。噉就令到一啲中小藝團嗰個財務嘅壓力冇咁冇咁大啦。咁另外就如果你做長期嘅演出嘅時候，我哋只會係嗰。
個base咧先至係一定會收嘅收入，咁完全就係另外嗰八個percent就睇佢嗰個誒票房咧嚟先至定到我哋最最終嗰個整體嗰個收入咯。好唔該，阿陳淑莊副主席，好簡短嘅啫。即係第一咧就誒，我想問下咧，以後咧呢啲紙，因為你知啦，而家我哋有三紙兩。
交噉樣嘅新政策，呢啲紙唔知可唔可以回收？即係可能我哋我諗立法會整體個政策都可能要考慮一下，因為我見到咧沓嘢兩沓嘢都好厚㗎，係啦。咁咧就誒，所以可能即係以後我哋要要諗一諗啦嚇。咁第二樣嘢咧就誒誒誒誒盡希望儘量用單一。
語言呢個好似都係做主席嘅時候咧，有個噉樣，因為等翻譯嗰個容易啲，唔好介意啊嚇。我明白有陣時都係誒誒，未必可以即係即時轉到轉到個語言嘅，但係希望大家儘量。我另外咧就係想問下咧，就係關於誒頭先個投影片嗰度咧，有一個話誒係即係主要係西九管理局製作，我就想。
問下誒喺咩情況之下西九管理局會決定係由佢自己製作嘅，即係譬如話頭先，我聽到阿阿張女士講，即係譬如話會去邀請啦、去發掘啦。咁但係喺咩時候你哋會決定係自行去製作咧，或者聯合製作等等？因為我見到咧，因為喺租場嘅時候你哋會有優先權，噉我都。
presenting。
如何選擇？
什麼係啲criteria？
我咁誒，如果要達到呢個效果嘅話，你哋會唔會誒？
好，啊，我再講句啫。
In term, if I understand correctly, your question is about the timelines of opportunities, or or how do you determine? You know, what is the criteria?
Okay, Mr. Chairman, just as a general point, what we're what we're targeting is around 10% of the usage within the time frame available. So it's not going to dominate, but it will supplement.好，啊，最後啦，姚思榮議員。
理解嘅，但係我就想誒瞭解下，即係去到咩程度，你哋先會哇，我先有機會被被被挑選為咧係可以喺西九嗰度係即係西九進行製作嘅，咁同埋會有啲咩誒特殊嘅，即係有冇啲咩特別嘅即係待遇噉樣咧？主席噉啊，我加多個會唔會有？
幾多比例啊？好嘛？好啊。Mr. Chairman, let me deal with the paper one. If members don't want the hard copies, we're very happy not to produce them.哦，唔緊要，唔係唔係唔係唔係，我我明白。唔係唔係，柏治唔關柏治高先生事，係我我哋我頭先講話係立法會啫嚇，即係阿阿柏治高先生，我哋唔係話緊你嚇，即係我哋都。
誒，關於誒西九自己做嘅製作嘅方向同埋挑選嘅方面，我講少少，跟住我交畀誒Alexson Poon李律講誒。其實每一個藝術場地最重要嘅就係建立佢自己一個藝術嘅性格同埋藝術嘅方向，令到我我哋西九嘅。
場地出到嚟嘅時候，唔會係同其他嘅場地所做嘅節目都係純粹係一樣。咁呢個原因就點解西九呢個場地喺香港所有嘅表演場地裏邊係第一個設立藝術總監呢一個職位。藝術總監呢個職位其實喺世界上所有嘅表演場地嚟。
所以藝術的criteria，係一個團隊努力。我們有專家在戲劇、舞蹈、音樂和四川。criteria，當然係關於質素。而我們都知道，如果我講錯，我最喜歡的説法係粵語，係「龍不拜太過有水」。challenge，我會翻譯成。
challenge of quality is as many people say beauty is in the eye of the beholder. However, I think what is important is what I said earlier about the focus first on Hong Kong artists, then Asia region and then global. So our priority leans towards Hong Kong, but it's ensuring that we provide diversity of the quality that we're.
誒，多謝主席。誒，我都係問一個問題，就係有關個觀眾拓展嗰度嚇。咁有關藝術表演誒，將來我哋面對一定係誒本地公誒本地觀眾啦，就海外同埋內地喺呢方面，唔知有冇一個預算，即係將來喺誒呢個客源個比例方面會達到咩一個效果？
誒同邊啲機構合作啊？咁即係大家一個互相互動，達到一個呢個效果咧。噉樣，仲有就誒未來嗰個誒宣傳推廣，你哋喺未來嗰個誒費用預算方面，會唔會做出一個噉嘅費用安排啊？咁達到呢個目標咧？噉樣。啊，柏志高先生。
Yes, let me answer the second one. Yes, of course we have a budget for both publicity and marketing, and that is an annual budget that's recurrent. It's built up based on the requirements of the museum, the performing arts, and then the general West Kalim Cultural District. That will be indicated.
The budget that we'll bring later in the year. In terms of our audience building and who the target is, well, honestly, we want to target all potential sources of audience. We we must market locally. We must market regionally. We must market internationally. Just to give you one example, we're talking currently with one of the major airlines.
to get publicity about the district at this stage of its development on their in-flight broadcasting system, because that covers both local, regional and long haul markets. That's just one example, but we have many different opportunities. One of the best opportunities actually is.
things like the Venice Biennale, because that raises our profile. Another good opportunity is our Basel in Hong Kong, because again, by participating in these things, the international and regional markets are there, but so are the local markets. So we want to cover all of the different market potential. We don't have a ratio.
趁住更換嘅時候，我講幾句，我唱。
誒旅發局嗰度，你哋會唔會同佢考慮合作咧？好，誒，姚議員畀一啲提議。
對唔住，我聽唔到話咩有兩個咩groups話咩話？啊，maybe maybe Louis can explain。
the tour guides, because I think that's an important way to let people know what is on here, so that when they're bringing groups in, they say, "Why don't you go to West Kowloon? That's what we want." 好，唔該曬，我問政協員。
一齊就誒，我仲話聽到蘿蔔青菜各有所愛，哇！呢個好厲害啦，真係好厲害嚇！I wish you could do it in Cantonese as well。誒就，我can have a go if you want。
You know, we don't want ten percent local, twenty-five percent regional, and the rest international. That doesn't work. It will depend on the programme. For a very Cantonese-speaking audience, of course, that wouldn't necessarily appeal to a long haul market. So you have to tailor your target depending on the nature.
各位，Patrick O'Shea， yes, as I said earlier, we do in fact have regular contact with both the tourism commission and the tourism board. We are talking to them about some joint marketing and getting involved in some of their marketing activities. We're also talking to the tourism board, as I said, about educating the.
誒嗱誒誒，當然係各花入各眼啦。咁但係你都有話係主動邀請本地嘅藝術團體嘅，就係主動嗰下咯。啊，我得你垂青，我當然係好高興啦。萬一我啊，我係真係非我係嗰啲誒邊緣嘅嚇，我係真係非常少做。
我嚟申請，但係我又唔夠錢啊！咁嚇，你你個西九文化區喺呢一方面，究竟即係同公眾嗰個誒個有冇對立嘅咧？你誒我又唔我我唔會主動邀請你啊！我覺得你唔夠班，即係好坦白講，第一嚇噉。第二你嚟。
申請啦，你又唔夠錢，噉啊真係對唔住啦。咁有冇噉樣嘅情況嘅咧？即係會唔會有啲扶持或者協助嘅計劃嘅咧？係啦。嗯嗯。嗯，Mr. Chairman，maybe I can start and then we can do it. Obviously there are funding schemes from government which they can tap into. We provide opportunities through Free Space, for example, where
We actually pay people to come and perform, and we have the street performer opportunity where there's almost no barrier to entry, so they will have opportunities. But on top of that, of course, we are looking, and I think Alison will will be able to describe this in better detail, at how we can develop our contacts throughout the artistic world so.
知得多。
thank you, Duncan.
係。
Okay. Greatness is on.
Great, so.
可能個方面呢？
呢呢個係上次個上一上一個嚟嘅呢個。
So, just need to get this PowerPoint up.
Many of the members are coming on the visit tomorrow, so we can show you around in detail.
Director of Project Control, who will take us through the first part, and then Alison and myself will supplement towards the end, Jeremy.
期第二期第三期噉樣樣嘅，咁第一期咧就會喺出年咧第二季起咧就會開放嘅啦。咁第二跟往後嘅期數咧，亦都會希望喺二零一九咧係陸陸續續係完成。咁呢個嘅空間咧會比喺而家嘅苗圃公園咧，即係我哋舉辦自由野嘅苗圃公園咧面積係更大，環境係更優美。
We're talking not just to the big nine, but we're talking to everybody. We want to be a venue where everybody from, for example, we put on two indie groups at one of our free space activities recently. They were picked up by an international event in Reykjavik in Iceland, and we supported their.
誒，其實有兩個例子咧，就係我哋點樣可以同一啲誒小型嘅團體或者比較邊緣嘅團體合作嘅。咁有個例子咧，就係誒香港有兩隊誒誒獨立嘅樂隊，一個人一隊叫做雞蛋蒸肉餅，另外一隊叫做A New World If You Can Take It。咁呢兩個團體咧都係一個比較小型嘅一個band，比較。
我聽你自己個band，噉我哋同發現到佢係一個好高嘅一個水準啦。噉我哋最近咧都安排佢去到誒冰島誒誒嘅首都嘅一個Airway Festival裏邊咧做一個誒世界嘅一個第一次出國嘅演出，咁都受到相當之受嘅歡迎。除此之外咧，我哋有一個叫做誒街頭誒表演。
嘅一個計劃，其實我哋已經做咗兩兩年幾嘅街頭表演嘅計劃咧，就係畀到唔同嘅自薦嘅覺得想喺誒西九嘅公園嘅公眾地方做街頭表演嘅一啲朋友咧，藉住一個好簡單嘅一個申請過過程咧，可以攞到一個一年嘅一個演出嘅牌照喺喺誒西九嗰度演出。咁呢個。
誒計劃咧，我到而家咧已經有三百幾個，即係誒香港嘅街頭表演者咧，係登記咗呢一個街頭嘅表演嘅計劃㗎。係啊，我諗呢個例子都幾好嘅，即係可能即係呢啲例子可以畀多啲大家知道，即係下嘅阿上邊有冇補充啊？雞蛋蒸肉餅，頭先我哋喺下一個。
個議程嗰度，我哋可以再係啦，係啦，係啦。好啊，噉啊，因為我哋即係遲咗十五分鐘即係開會啦，咁所以問下問下啲時間都緊迫。噉我哋不如進入下一個議程啦，好嘛？嗯。咁下一個議程咧就藝術公園同埋自由空間發展嘅最新進展。噉啊，有冇啲同事要跟換咧？要要跟換或者。
啊，噉就下一個議程就係誒西九公園嘅發展啦。呢一個項目咧，我哋對上翻嚟誒呢個誒委員會報告咧，都已經係幾年前啦。咁實在咧，藝術公園咧都已經有一個好誒，即係令人誒欣喜嘅發展，因為咧其實出年咧就會係第一期嘅公園嘅開幕㗎啦。咁藝術公園咧。
係當然係西九一個好重要嘅部分啦。除咗係畀市民咧誒一個休憩消閒嘅公共空間咧，會係即係誒開放畀市民使用啦，亦都會係一個好嶄新嘅户外文化藝術活動空間嚟嘅。咁西九管理局咧就會分三期完成啦。大家喺文件嘅附件嗰度咧都睇到咧，我哋有誒叫做第一期。
公園裏邊嘅主要嘅藝術設施咧，就包括喺舊年七月已經啟用咗嘅M加展亭啦，同埋咧今將會喺明年年底落成嘅自由空間。自由空間咧將會係提供一個可靈活使用嘅黑盒劇場，誒大概係四百五十座位嘅，同埋咧一個多用途室。而户外嘅草坪嘅表演場地咧，更加有一個咧係容納超過一。
一萬位觀眾嘅多用途表演場地嘅係適合一啲户外音樂會同埋其他嘅表演。咁西郊管理局咧，而家正係密羅緊鼓咁咧，為藝術公園同埋自由空間咧嘅啟用係做好準備。噉我係先請阿柏志高先生咧係講一講誒，介紹一下，或者請其他同事。好，柏志高先生。I'd just like to introduce Jeremy Steward.
嗯。
Hong Kong Island in the background.
Their permanent location in the main park, around the the main lawn and free space building.
F and M and E, and there should be no reason why you know this building is delayed in any sense in in opening up later this year.
So just to start with a few visuals, this is a nice visual looking from the M+ museum westwards, and you can see the Hong Kong Island in the background.
We also have the two existing structures in this park: the one that belongs to the MTRC Airport Railway, and also the Western Harbour Tunnel Building, which we have to build around.
About the third quarter of 2018, so I think you can see that in 2018 it's going to be a very exciting period for the park opening up and the promenade, which really does have spectacular views for the public to enjoy.
So just another view. This is looking from east to west. This will be the entrance to the free space building, and that sort of curved wall to the left. You know, landscaping will be around there to take people up towards the promenade area.
Go the full length of the development, and here you can just see the M+ building in the background. This is the retail, dining and entertainment space, which is down near the promenade for people people to enjoy.
Thank you, Chairman. Good morning, Members. Great pleasure today to present an update on the development of the art park and free space within the art park. So we have a few slides to show you visuals and obviously construction update, and I believe.
Second one here is a rendering, again looking from west to east, so you can see the free space building, which is embedded in the landscape, and obviously to the left the paths which go through to the promenade, again with
Third visual here is the promenade, and I think members may know there's a sort of big strip of around 20 odd metres that's from the seafront, that's completely free, and it has hard paving and soft landscape as well, and it'll.
So, in delivering the art park, there are three phases that's shown on the screen. There, phase one, phase two, phase three. Phase one, we're almost there. We've submitted our forms to the relevant statutory authorities just this week.
And we hope hope to open up certainly the promenade area of phase one very early in the new year. Certainly, there will be a period in that phase one where the grass and the trees need a period of time to bed in, and that will.
happen in the first quarter of 2018. If we move further east, you can then see the phase two and the phase three area, and that green area in the middle is the free space building, which is due to be completed in about.
所以你可見，從這視覺，十三個元素到公園，包括到北面。目前，育苗圃，和你會見到一些後續的幻燈片，很多樹木現在從育苗圃進入。
如果。
樹。
Sorry, Duncan. Yeah.
where。
and something like.
散佈喺周圍嘅公園。
Just a couple of other visuals of of this dining and entertainment space that we will have at the promenade.
When they're transplanted over, that they need to settle down and bed in, but we think over the next few months, hopefully they will all they will all take.
And above the retail, we call it sort of a double curve. Public will be able to wander on top, so you get an even more spectacular view of Hong Kong Island.
And you can see, this is a view from south to north, and you can see the retail spaces, which are set back from the promenade, which people will be able to enjoy sitting out there when when they're opened up.
So just a quick slide there showing the promenade. It's granite paved blocks, and there's a low height wall. And as I said, this will stretch all the way around the waterfront, unimpeded, for people to walk, jog, take their dogs for a walk, etc.
So here's a, I think this was taken just a couple of weeks ago, the free space building which sits in the middle of the park. It was topped out in around July, earlier this year, and so we're now concentrating on the external finishes, the internal ABW.
And at the promenade area to the west, you can see that here. This is an aerial view of the retail, dining and entertainment space, which is below. As you can see, it's sort of embedded into the park. So landscaping will be over the top of it, so it will not look intrusive.
So on the planting aspect, forgive me, I'm not a tree expert, but we have a few slides to to show some of the trees. But you can see here with this planting concept, what our designers have done as regards where the where there are flowering trees, canopy.
etc. spread spread around the park, and I think they've achieved a really nice balance between some sort of open lawn area, soft landscaping, and obviously the facilities like free space and the M+ Pavilion. And intertwined among that is obviously things like toilet block.
So, for those who know a little bit more about trees, some of the species there that are getting planted in the section one of the park, which a number of these have been growing for up to three years in the nursery park, so they have a period.
Ask colleagues about some more information about the trees. Just for members' reference, we will have at least two thousand trees and over two hundred thousand shrubs and plants within this park area. Over fifty percent of the trees are our native species. It's very important. They have to be suitable.
啊，Louis。
Okay, you can continue.
and the.
Did Louis want to interject now?
topped out, and we'll be putting a lot of events on there.
And the free space building as well, which we've touched on earlier, is also.
And you can see there some of the shrubs etc. to which CEO is referring as well.
之後咧，我哋會繼續將佢誒擴展同埋繼續嚟去應用嘅。多謝主席。不如你叫曬所有啲共享單車去曬西九啦，譬如。
Yes, 512 out of 936 trees. I think we've we've put in the paper there from the nursery park to the to the main art park.
So again, just one or two more slides on the tree species that we've already transplanted in the phase one area.
success, even though a little bit little bit of difficulty getting to the access because there's a lot of construction going on around it, but still it's it's doing great.
七十%， just under seventy percent of the trees from the nursery park will be transplanted into the main park. The remainder are simply not not suitable or, unfortunately, haven't survived. So we we have made very good use of that nursery park experience. 譬如我哋上次視察嘅時，好似都介紹過啦。其實都
Okay, so final few slides. Just to touch on the facilities that are located in the art park. Many of you already know we have the M Plus Pavilion, which was referred to earlier, which was opened in 2016. Continues to be a great.
主席，誒除此之外咧，我哋誒喺呢幾年裏邊都係嘗試緊一啲唔同嘅用嚟喺將來西九公園開幕咗之後，我哋會繼續嘅活動。第一就係一個遊遊西嘅誒西九嘅單車服務啦。我哋喺二零一四年嘅推出係香港首個單車共享嘅計劃，由社會企業嚟到營運，到而家嚟講咧超過四。
二萬五千個使使用者㗎啦，仲有另外一個就頭先我提過嘅一個街頭表演計劃，我哋喺二零一五年八月嘅時候推出，到而家咧已經發出三百九十八個街頭表演嘅許可證。咁呢兩個咧都係喺西九誒，以全港嚟講，我哋首先推出嘅項目。咁誒，我哋都係覺得係相當之成功喺西九嘅公園開。
誒噉啊好啦，噉啊多謝介紹啦，噉我哋就開放畀委員啦。噉我想講講啦，誒，因為我哋其實呢一間房咧，即係十點九會有人用，咁所以我最最多就算延長都係到十點八嘅，咁所以我哋都即係大家自己提問都因住啲時間啦，好嘛？噉啊四。
啊！都。
阿Lisa。
多謝主席。
正係有效一年嘅，我記憶中嚇。
describe the content of their performance. That's not our job. But perhaps Lisa can deal with the other questions.
誒，多謝毛議員嘅提問。誒，頭先你講到水平方面，咁其實誒，街頭表演都有高低嘅唔同嘅水平嘅。街頭表演係一個冇，我冇提過水平嘅問題。
分鐘誒，連麥連達、黃萬正議員誒，唔該曬主席。就我想問清楚咧，你街頭表演嗰度咧誒，所有嘅細節我知㗎啦，就唔需要花時間重複嚇。即係譬如申請嗰個許可證就有一年後啊嚇誒，表演每次誒起碼要五分。
鐘啊！等等，即係個時間，朝頭早十點到夜晚十點，就每節啊兩個鐘頭到噉，一一定要離開嗰個位置嘅表演完畢，就四個鐘頭之後又去第二度啊！等等，我完全知道嘅。啊，問題係咧，就首先第一呢一個。
噉樣嘅街頭表演咧，就承接翻正話講嘅嚇，會唔會變成有一個等級嘅分別？就係你呢啲咧係誒並非係受邀請嘅巴閉嘅嚇，就誒係誒街頭嘅啫。咁會唔會誒有畀人有個等級嘅感覺？第一，第二咧？
即係誒，即使你話噉係當然，街頭表演最叻嘅就係嗰個即興嘅感覺啊。但係而家咧，你就變咗全部係好啊誒，即係已經係佈置過曬，已經好似即係配藥噉樣咧，配好曬出嚟嘅。就呢個係其二，即係當中嗰種誒。
即係令人誒感覺有啲突兀啊！你明我意思嚇。即係呢一方面，你又唔係正統式偉大誒喺劇院表演，但係第二咧，你又唔係真係好似好街頭嘅嗰種啊誒即興嘅感覺。誒呢個係我嘅誒，即係我作為觀眾。
嘅一個感覺啦嚇，而第二咧就係佢攞許可證要畀錢嘅。但係你正話又話，其實係你哋畀錢佢嚟誒街頭表演嘅添。呢一個我就誒唔係太過明白。問咗呢度先，或者呢一個可能你哋詳細解答一下，無議員啊嘛。
Yeah, I'll actually ask Lisa to answer most of it, but let me make a couple of things clear. First, we don't prescribe what they perform; that's entirely up to them. We just prescribe where they perform, and it's it's it's basically to ensure that they don't block access, they don't block emergency vehicle routes, etc. So we we certainly don't prescribe
我唔想話誒，其實街頭表演咧都有佢自己本身不同嘅水平啦。噉我哋其實而家嗰個街頭表演嘅政策咧就冇分到話大家嘅高低嘅。咁基本上佢入嚟誒，我哋睇佢哋嗰個表演嘅時候咧，真係唔好意思，我唔夠時間嚇就誒。我其實係想問你呢頭話係你哋畀錢佢入嚟表演。
係。
哦。
好。
我冇聽錯。
好，阿陳淑莊副主席。
第一期嗰度。
誒多謝主席，噉就誒。
盡係可以發到幾多張證嘅咧？
好似係就住第一階段嗰個位置嘅。
首先咧，我就想問，因為頭先誒誒阿阿。
案咧，即係咩咩嚟㗎咧？就頭先我介頭先玩得誒，即係個投影片有少少，但係我想了解第三期其實係咩嚟㗎？
發得少咯，就係而家其實係佢哋自己主動主動申請嘅係嘛？冇錯，係佢主動申請嘅。
我知佢亦都可以攞到捐款嘅表演之後嚇，但係掉轉頭嗰個許可證要收錢㗎嘛？係嗰個許可證咧係一個一百蚊嘅收費嚟㗎，咁一個一年嘅證啦，係冇錯一百蚊嘅證。嗱我跟住好快，因為得四分鐘啊嘛。我想問埋咧，你就三百九十八個證出咗嗰誒誒每個。
如果計起嚟咧，就大概係誒廿九個月，你發出咗咁多個證，就平均每個月咧誒大概十四張到嘅啫。即使係兩三日先發出一張，呢個我想知道，如果你係誒將來咩都開曬之後，最
啊，其實好好誒，其實法證咧係冇一個上限嘅，因為其實最主要嚟講就係佢哋幾時嚟表演啦。咁其實我哋係就喺度誒觀察咗咁耐咧，唔同嘅表演者有唔同佢哋自己嘅需求嘅。咁有啲中意羣眾，有一啲中意比較靜局嘅地方。噉係咪唔同嘅表演有唔同嘅需要啦？咁所以其實我哋暫時嚟講冇設。
Jeremy係嘛係啦，佢佢誒做介紹嘅時候咧，佢就提出咗咧，就話今個禮拜啱啱有個申請，唔好意思，我啱啱嗰度咧錯過咗，可唔可以重複一次啊，主席？同埋關於涉及啲咩範圍，有個好似係向係咪城規定係咩部門申請，噉啊畀多少資料，唔好意思。
Yes, you did. We have sent in the standard statutory forms to both the fire services department and the buildings department to open phase one area of the park. 好好唔該曬。咁咧，啊啊，主席，另外咧，我。
想問下第三期嗰度啊，即係就住呢一個藝術公園，因為咧就誒，其實都好趕啊，因為誒你見到咧就誒誒一七跟住出年係㗎啦，係啦，咁但係咧第三期咧文件嗰度咧都少交代嘅，咁所以我就想了解下究竟第三期嗰個誒其實係係咩咩事？
The fees fee.
誒，主席，我想誒。
誒有冇一個從長者嘅角度係一個長者友善嘅一個政策？
即係要從用家角度啊，講下個藝術公園啦。噉我就誒嗱啲咁靚嘅草地畀人坐就好好啦。咁但係咧就誒。
誒推出嘅，咁而家呢兩個嗰個誒計劃係點咧？仲會唔會推出？定係誒會整體會喺誒咁多場地開放之前咧，會復檢翻呢個指引一次咧？唔該曬主席。好。
人流去欣賞佢哋嘅表演咧，咁先要會多啲其他嘅表演者咯，係啦。多謝。我個擔心工作證啫，主席，不過已經跳咗跳咗線嘅咧，即係即係嗰啲街頭表演者嗰啲工作證，即係簽證嗰啲，遲啲先係啦。黃碧雲議員。
I've just put it up on the screen. There, phase three, underneath phase three is an interfacing car park which has about 205 car parking spaces. That structure is almost completed. It's being built under the M.
M Plus Main Works Contract. Once that structure is fully fitted out and complete, we will then ask the contractor that's building the park to come back into that space when it's handed over from the M Plus Main Works Contractor, and he will do all of the soft soft landscaping.
好唔該曬。另外咧，就係關於都係街頭表演嗰個嗰個計劃。誒，坦白講，我都研究過其他地方，有啲直情要有一個試聽，即係要要表演先再發牌嘅。咁而家喺西九咧，其實誒。
即係誒，可能好多交流嘅節目，但係你話如果真係有表演嘅話咧，就即係唔係話成日有好多活動喺嗰度噉，所以咧就可能即係個街嗰個發牌嗰個數目未必係咁多。但係我想了解一下咧，譬如話去到將來即係當西九局部嘅地方都開曬啦，即係尤其是一八年，我諗你哋好期待啦。
咁誒會唔會喺就住發牌嗰度有多少少即係誒整體啲嘅政策咧？因為我而家睇到咧就誒，如果我冇睇錯嘅話，你哋主要咧而家都係嗰個西九交頭誒街頭表演指引咧，就係二零一六年七月嘅版本嚟嘅啫。咁誒就住而家誒嚟緊咁多。
新嘅表演場地啊，或者甚至啲公共地方咧，誒開放嘅話咧，會唔會有其他嘅要求？咁當年咧嗱，誒有一個西九文化區街頭表演者計劃嘅，咁同埋對上咧第六段咧就有個叫少年者誒少年表演者，咁咧嗰度嗰陣時都括弧寫住咧，就話要稍後階段。
多謝主席，多謝你嘅提問。誒，講翻嗰個少年表演者同埋西九文化區嗰個表演者交流表演者計劃啦。咁呢一個其實我哋係誒有待我哋個誒整體成個誒西九文化區發展之後再會去睇嘅原因係其實我哋喺呢一個苗圃公園嘅時候，我哋亦都有考亦都去有考究呢一件事情啦。噉就發
個其實誒十六歲以下嘅朋友咧，就唔係咁多嘅。咁而其實香港因為工作比較繁忙啦，噉就發覺而家唔係咁多呢啲噉嘅表演者嘅，噉就發覺都未必需要去推出咯。咁而我哋而家暫時個誒，而另外一個西九文化區嘅表演者呢一個咧，就希望嗰個有有若干嘅藝術水平嘅門檻嘅。咁而呢一
有一張圖咧，你好似有上下兩層。
係咪嗰邊都係碼頭咧？No，that was a that was a previous example. That location is not suitable on the left hand side.所以只係得北面同埋誒東南面嗰邊會有碼頭。咁呢個碼頭會唔會喺公園第一期開幕嘅時候已經有渡輪？
一個藝術水平嘅門檻咧，暫時嚟講，我哋喺街頭表演呢一幾年嗰個嘅觀察咧，亦都係誒未必去到一個成熟嘅階段啊。咁因為我哋而家本身嗰個誒嗰個誒嘅執嗰個嗰個牌照咧，係唔分嗰個國籍嘅，就算係外國人，我哋都會發畀佢嘅。咁而外國人嗰個一般。
般嚟講，因為佢哋有呢一個文化咧，嗰個水平係比較高一啲啦。咁但係佢哋亦都唔選擇喺文化區嗰度表演太多嘅，因為佢哋需要人流啊。因為當佢哋需要有嗰個捐獻嘅時候，佢需要嗰人流去資助佢哋嗰個誒不停去唔同嘅地方嘅演出啦。噉我哋亦都睇到就係我哋要等到文化區去發展之後有若干嘅人流，足夠嘅人。
即係你叫啲老人家佢坐睇咧，佢起唔到身嘅。咁所以我我我比較concern有冇椅嘅，即係呢一個公園，即係有冇避雨亭嘅。即係因為咧，誒一落起雨嘅時候咧，佢哋都唔知要閃去邊啊個公園嗰度。噉啊，即係我見到你。
即係嗰個數碼嗰個嗰嗰張圖咧，就好似誒嗰度有一個長廊噉，下邊好似有啲椅噉。我見到有兩張噉，我我希望係有足夠嘅椅咧，等大家係真係可以坐喺度hea下休息下。佢有時唔係想去做咩嘅。
可能真係想去欣賞下呢一個公園噉，所以咧即係需要有足夠誒有有有有病嘅佢可以撳到，即係起身嘅好方便，可以啲老人家坐到嘅咁嗰個shelter啦，即係嗰啲如果落雨啊，好曬嘅時候，即係我哋係有。
要設想埋唔同嘅季節，誒落雨、晴天、好熱、好凍。咁究竟個公園係咪有足夠嘅呢啲係從誒用家嘅角度嘅嗰啲嘅設施？我我想問一問嗰個情況。好，我記得公園好似好多可以自由搬動嘅燈嘅噉啊。
不，不令人高興哈。There's there's a number of facilities for the elderly, which I think will be very attractive. For example, if you look at this shot here, both sides all the way along the promenade will be seats. So they are at a comfortable seating height and they give an unobstructed view.
出和入公園。如果我們轉到這雙邊，你會也見到，內雙邊不僅會有座位，而且會有遮蔽物。除此之外，公園內還有遮蔽座位。如果你到過我們
For example, we also have a system of casual seats which we make available for anybody. They can have them at any time. I think at the moment we have about 30 odd, and we certainly anticipate having something similar in in the the final park. On top of which, of course, free.
就係要考試嘅。
嗯，OK，OK。
好，梁美芬議員。
etc. by the opening of the M plus.
嗰種乜嘢都考試啊！我同佢哋温習嘅時候，我都揼埋啊！
我點樣教藝術？一班同學五十個percent會唔合格㗎？
點解咧？其實從一開始講西九文化區，我已經提到。
明明好中意藝術嘅人咧，係抌曬，因為考完嗰啲試咧，就唔想再見到藝術。
噉你點樣搞咧？呢一樣嘢咧，我係好希望講過好多次咧。你哋誒管理局係要同教育局傾嘅。
乜嘢都係考試。我嗰個年代都仲未使考試，都係畫下掃誒誒咩誒誒掃描啊嚇。大家而家考試全部背咗啲畫係複印版。
係八年前開始，因為咧當時咧，我經歷咗咧就係誒我自己嘅兩個誒小朋友，佢讀中學嘅時候嘅藝術教育。
去誒享受去欣賞藝術。你話你話外國嗰啲誒表演者嗰個水平高啲，我哋即係係冇咁高啦。咁可能嚟欣賞嘅人可能都有調轉嘅情況，就係我哋根本冇去欣賞，唔識去欣賞嘅人。
傷心嘅意思咧，就係即係香港第一咧，自己咧對於藝術嗰個所謂消費者，即係識欣賞藝術，肯去誒去或者畀錢，甚至去花費佢嘅時間去欣賞嘅人咧，係唔夠。
本身會有空間，會有咖啡廳和RDE設施，再次會對所有人開放，但當然除了長者之外，我認為公園內應有足夠的設施。
on top of that we're also looking at how do we get people around the park because as you say some people may not be very mobile so if you come tomorrow you'll see for yourself we have an autonomous vehicle under trial at the moment which is intended for elderly for disabled people with young children so that we can
哦，facilitate their access to the park as well。好誒，跟住我想問咧，就係個碼頭同埋渡輪啦。咁呢個公園就好正，即係我哋希望好多人可以嚟，好方便咁嚟。噉就誒，我想問下咧，就喺藝術公園咧，我而家見到個圖嘅誒。
右下角係咪好似嗰度係應該有個碼頭，可以等啲船可以喺嗰度上岸嘅咧？或者係咪已經聯係緊有關嘅公司，係誒會提供一啲渡輪等誒香港？即係其實呢個公園啱就喺喺維港一個好靚嘅一個位。噉我想問下碼頭個安。
安排係咪會有喺右下角嗰度？Mr Chairman, yes, indeed, we are. In fact, if you look at this this image, to the the bottom right hand corner, you can see that there is a ferry pier indicated. We're we're currently talking to the Marine Department, Transport Department, Tourism Commission, to
secure their government support for this. Certainly, we are prepared to to operate a ferry pier, and indeed we're looking at perhaps a second one in the northern part of the site, adjacent to the exhibition centre hub, because we believe that would be also a good way to bring people to the both the park and the exhibition.左邊左邊左邊。
可以拍到即係運到啲人過嚟。Well, no, we won't have a ferry service for the phase one of the park. The intention is that, given the time it'll take to develop and construct this, it'll take us a couple of two to three years at least. So we're talking as if if we can get it in place in time through all the permits from government.
係主席，多謝。誒，喺呢個誒誒西九嗰個誒發展咧，噉我都好高興，而家你哋有藝術公園啊，有呢一方面嘅。但係咧，即係誒坦白講咧，頭先聽到阿張女士講嘅回應咧，即係就即係令我哋其實係誒好傷心。
消費者嘅喎。
你做藝術家都係要有人去參與佢先係可以成為佢嘅一個career㗎。
regularly get 10,000 people to come along to Free Space. We regularly get
佢好主動，佢會去，佢會揾曬呢啲嘢。但係，譬如頭先張張小姐講嘅，如果係另外一啲藝術，會唔會咁多人去參與咧？咁根本嗰啲人生存唔到。
嚇噉，所以咧呢一啲可能我哋係需要額外嘅輔助，甚至我覺得一開始嘅時候可能要有資源嘅輔助佢哋，先慢慢可以survive到啊！
即係我覺得，如果我哋嘅藝術教育唔係配，即係要配套成個西九文化區，你而家有呢個所謂大白，點解我哋成日話大白象？好啦，而家冇咁大白象，大家好多idea擺咗落去起緊，你冇人去欣賞，冇人冇呢一個文化，你點樣西九文化區？特別。
下一代，所以我認為咧，你哋即係而家，我哋開始有啲，我連公園我都認為係硬件，但係我哋可以係welcome多啲人。但係你唔係有呢個長遠嘅內涵喺度咧，即係我哋呢個西九文化區，我哋自己誒唔同年代嘅人可以去。
你教藝術用呢種嘅考試嘅方式，所以我認為咧呢一個你哋唔配套咧，你個非緊文化區都係虛嘅。我哋喺邊度揾啲人去欣賞人哋嘅藝術？第二咧，我就好高興啦，喺三廿八point三廿八有個自由約咧，即係我自己去做個即係消費參與者啦。我帶。
嗰次就係誒係pet lover嚇帶誒小狗去嘅，大家好多人一齊去享受嗰次係自發嘅民間嘅。我認為西九文化區就係即係多啲呢一啲嘅誒活動係非常之好，但係你都要facilitate啊，因為咧香港誒對就是年青人啦pet。
噉我我譬如我去自由約嗰次嘅經驗，就佢好多workshop，甚至有人喺度講lecture，就係講呢個噉嘅嘅topic，好多人一齊去參與，好開心。即係我真係好耐冇試過咁開心嘅一個晏晝。噉你其他嘅呢啲藝術嘅topic，你會唔會可能係冇咁多？
嚇噉，你哋點樣去facilitate我哋嘅社會去去參與呢啲藝術嘅活動？Patrick，先生，I'm Mr. Jim. I'm delighted you enjoyed Free Space. Please come on the 14th of January when we have our next one. We actually have a now developed a regular connection with a pet charity.
Dog rescue, and that's now become one of our regular features. And indeed, one of the things that we believe is is very very important is that this space is open to everybody. You were talking, unfortunately, you didn't come into the earlier part of the conversation this morning where we were talking in great detail about how we're working with schools with education.
喂。
呢個請翻誒阿莊小姐答啊！
係咪成個西九嘅範圍都可以容許佢嘅咧？
你點樣吸引現有嘅誒街頭表演者入嚟咧？
Mr. Chairman, I think the honourable member has put a finger immediately on the point. People get can get bothered by street performance if it's too noisy. If it's
裏邊用嘅，咁至於體育中心裏邊咧，我哋就會考慮喺其用啊用節目嘅模式咧去表演，係去展示咯。好，啊黃敏政議員最後啦。
能夠完成咗之後咧，而西九又起到佢個碼頭咧，我哋咧就希望能夠將來係提供到呢個水上的士嘅服務。係，即係講得點嘅，因為個Poplar Wood咧係可以去埋中環同埋。呢度咧嗱，我頭先都講咗啦，我哋最盡都去到達八嘅啫。咁仲有無議員？噉我。
或者你嘅遊輪咧喺誒，有你可以分peak hours同埋唔係peak hours咯。有啲係可以，甚至你要同嗰個船公司去傾咧，係誒要跨，我都覺得你哋都要係跨局嘅去諗，可能要運防局都要參與埋嘅。咁呢度可能常備你要幫下手啦。誒，呢呢度簡單。
Talking about how we can bring children into our exhibitions. Children coming into Free Space, for example. Indeed, the next Free Space will have Oh My Kids as a specific target at young people, because obviously they are the audience of the future. And one of the things that is so important for us is about cultivating.
The audience. And again, we talked in great detail about that in the earlier part of the meeting this this afternoon. So I won't repeat that. But I will say, one of the key issues from our point of view is that we want this space to be for everybody. We want it to be attractive. So, for example, we
twenty twenty five thirty thousand people coming for events such as clock and flap, so they are mass audiences for these. and we're talking about what is an insubstantial park at the moment. This is within the nursery park. Once we have the proper park, honestly, hand on heart, there will be a lot more people visiting because it will be much much more.
substantial much more attractive, and of course on top of that, as we again described earlier, we will be programming in free space on the on the giant lawn throughout the district. So I don't want to get into detail because I have.我我追問一一小一點嘅，即係呢個一一路跟㗎啦，跟咗好多年，就係誒頭先咧就誒同事。
亦都提到咧，就係話誒會唔會有嗰個水上誒交通、水上的士啦？我記得我哋好早就走嚟揾你哋嘅誒管理局，就提出water taxi嘅概念啦。噉我其實呢一樣嘢咧，啊，我係想你哋當誒真係落成有呢個你用ferry係好事嚟嘅，即係大但係可以。
誒慢慢噉樣誒誒去誒做嗰個誒誒site visit，即係睇到嗰個我哋睇到好靚嘅誒維港，又可以用到嗰個水路嘅交通。我希望你接駁嗰個啟德郵輪碼頭，即係如果你哋去plan嘅時候咧，因為我哋喺啟德郵輪碼。
頭嗰邊咧，誒九龍城區議會咧，就一路希望咧，我哋嗰個誒遊輪嘅服務咧，可以打橫，因為嗰邊咧又係山卡拉，係嗰邊咧就嘥到咧地方，即係人人都即係誒誒鬧得好緊要㗎啦。係噉，你如果嗰度嘅有一個水上嘅的士服務。
多謝阿劉議員嘅誒提問。其實咧誒希望西九能夠有一個水上嘅運輸嘅誒安排咧，呢個其實喺呢個聯合小組委員會都提咗好多次。我亦都承諾咗咧，將誒各位議員啦，同埋係誒西九管理局嘅期望咧，係反映咗畀政府嘅。咁而家其實誒政府內部咧都係研究緊呢一
一個嘅可行性，當然，如果西九自己要獨力去承擔一條嘅水上的士嘅路線咧，呢個係有困難嘅。咁但係如果能夠連接埋其他嘅一啲景點，包括頭先梁議員提嘅啟德，誒將來有體育園啦，亦都有遊輪碼頭，同埋有好多嘅新發展。呢啲咧，我哋而家都係考慮當中。咁但係誒，仲需要一段時間先可以完成到嗰個研究喺。
最多我問好短嘅啫，我問少少就係我想問咧，就係而家呢個即係街頭表演許可證咧，就係可以喺自由夜嗰度啊，即係同埋藝術公園嗰度表演啦，係嘛？咁如果西九將來開放多啲，噉佢去到例如啊，即係粵曲，即係戲曲中心出邊，係咪都可以表演咧？
多謝主席嘅提問。啊啊，我哋其實嗰個誒誒街頭表演嗰個嗰個誒指引咧，係適合喺所有嘅誒户外嘅空間嘅public open space嘅。咁所以喺嗰個戲曲中心出邊嗰個地方咧，都係係屬於嗰個誒嘅範圍嘅。咁所以呢一個嘅街頭表演嘅指引係可以喺誒戲曲中心裏。
好快趣問一問啫，就係誒你嗰個街頭表演咧，你就話係冇內容限制啊，等等嚇，亦都冇話教佢表演乜嘢。問題係內容係有限制㗎咯，尤其是你將來係開放曬整個誒我哋嘅文化區嗰度。
你入面寫都明嘅指引，話即係內容啊，唔好令人反感啊。噉我諗包括噪音啦，當然，然後佢嗰啲表演嘅器具，你要求佢係三分鐘之內可以全部移走嗱。呢一啲噉樣嘅規限，你點樣吸引到而家喺啊旺角行人專用區嘅？
啊！街頭表演者入嚟咧，依日喺旺角咧就當然我都好喜歡街頭表演，但係問題係誒住喺旺角嘅一啲嗰區嘅一啲市民咧，就覺得個噪音啊等等係誒有滋擾成分嘅。噉你而家有整個西九文化區，但係你又有諸多限制。
得啦，夠鍾。好。
Frankly, if it doesn't sound very good, what we are trying to do is to say, look.
To be to be frank with you, I'm not entirely sure we want to attract certain types of certain types of street performer.
This is an open approach. They can choose to come to us. What we will do is, when we see someone that is good enough for us to support, then we will support them. But for someone who's not good enough, well, fine, they can come, but we're not going to attract them.
去即係三點鐘去西九視察，噉啊，我哋都好多人嘅十一個啊議員會去視察，噉啊，期待住聽日啊，你哋可以帶我哋去睇睇最新嘅進展。多謝大家，今日嘅會議結束。
好唔該曬嗱噉啊！呢個議程亦都即係誒完啦。噉啊，其他事項係冇嘅。咁最後咧，提提大家委員啦。聯合小組委員會咧，下一次嘅會議喺二零一八年二月九日上午八點半至十點半。
兩件事，安全。如果你係occupying a space that's within， for example， an emergency vehicle access point， you have to be able to move quickly。那please， I do know the constraints。 I'm asking you how you're going to lure， attract existing street performers into the district。
噉啊，會討論兩項嘅議題嘅，即係大家都好關心㗎啦。噉啊，西九文化區計劃嘅最新財務狀況同埋加強財務安排嘅最新進展，同埋呢個戲曲中心發展嘅最新進展。當日應該主席會過嚟講係嘛？O.K.噉啊，聽日咧，我哋應該會再見嘅，因為聽日我哋都。